Guide to the Capt. James A. Baker correspondence, clippings, and photographs collection MS 487
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Capt. James A. Baker correspondence, clippings, and photographs collection
1874-1951
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Baker, James Addison
MS 487
6 Linear Feet 4 boxes
Correspondence from Capt. James A. Baker (Rice Institute Chairman, 1891-1941) to various family members and colleagues, newsclippings regarding William M. Rice and regarding Capt. Baker's death, and photographs of the Baker family.
Biographical Note
Capt. James A. Baker was a prominent attorney in the law firm of Baker, Botts & Baker, who represented many wealthy citizens, one of whom was William Marsh Rice, founder of Rice University. In 1891, Baker was made a member of the Rice Institute Board of Trustees and eventually became Chairman of the Board. After Rice's death in 1900, a suspicious Capt. Baker alerted authorities to the possibility of foul play. Because of his efforts, investigators discovered that Rice was in fact murdered by an associate.
As Chairman of the Board, Baker contributed to the establishment of Rice University an elite educational institution. Because of his business savvy, the Rice endowment was more than doubled in the early years of the university. Mr. Baker served as Chairman until his death on Aug. 2, 1941. His son, James A. Baker, Jr., served in World War II, became a lawyer in the family firm and continued the Baker commitment to Rice.
James A. Baker III., Capt. Baker's grandson, was born in 1930 to the wealthy Baker family and attended Princeton University. He joined the military and spent two years as a marine lieutenant. After his stint in the military, Baker attended University of Texas School of Law and began a career as a lawyer which lasted until his wife's death in 1970. At the urging of his friend George H. W. Bush, Baker ran for the Senate. He lost the Senate race, but went on to serve as chief of staff and Secretary of the Treasury in President Ronald Reagan's administration and as Secretary of State under George Bush. He has had a hand in the management of every Republican campaign for president from 1976 to 1992. After his career in politics Baker returned to working as an attorney and became a member Baker Botts law firm.
On June 2, 1992, Dr. Richard J. Stoll, Director for the Center for the Study of Institutions and Values, as well as a professor of Political Science, sent a memo to then Rice President George Rupp, suggesting that Rice approach then Secretary of State James A. Baker III for the beginnings of a "James Baker Institute". Rupp responded favorably to Stoll's memo and thus the Baker Institute was born. On March 31, 1993, Secretary Baker gave a speech accepting Rice's offer of an Institute in his honor, laying down his ideas on the Baker Institute. In this speech, entitled Ideas Into Action, in which he charged the Baker Institute to "draw together statesmen, scholars and students...and...build a bridge between the world of ideas and the world of action..." These founding words were later used as the building stones for the external architecture of the building.
The Honorable James A. Baker, III would later served on the Rice Board of Trustees from 1993 to the present day, currently acting as Trustee Emeretus.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence from Capt. James A. Baker (Rice Institute Chairman, 1891-1941) to various family members and colleagues, newsclippings regarding William M. Rice and regarding Capt. Baker's death, and photographs of the Baker family.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research. Boxes 1-2 stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Acquisition Information
This collection was a gift donated by Alice Baker Jones Meyer through Mrs. Ray Watkin Strange, Jan. 2000.
Related Materials
See Baker Family papers, 1853-1971, MS 40, Woodson Research Center.
See Baker Family "Information Files", Woodson Research Center.
Arrangement
Missing Title
Series I: Correspondence 1874-1951 (10 folders)
Series II: Newsclippings, scrapbooks and published materials, 1920-1941, n.d. (5 folders, 2 scrapbooks, 1 box)
Series III: Family photographs, 1870-1940 (1 folder and 1 box)
General
Portions of this collection are available online at https://scholarship.rice.edu/handle/1911/77644
Index Terms
Subjects
Law and legislation; Rice University -- History; Business; Universities and colleges
Document Types
reports; photographs; corrrespondence; clippings (information artifacts)
Subjects (Persons)
Baker, James Addison; Baker, Alice Graham; Baker, James Addison, Judge; Baker, Rowena Crawford; Jones, Alice Baker; Baker family
- Series I: Correspondence 1874-1951, 27503
  - James A. Baker to father, Judge James A. Baker, 1874-75, 27514 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Judge James A. Baker to son, James A. Baker, 1875-1880; 27513 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - James A. Baker to mother, Rowena Baker, 1874-75, 27512 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Rowena Baker to son, James A. Baker, 1874, 27511 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - James A. Baker to sister, Minie Baker, 1874, 27510 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - James A. Baker to various family members, 27509 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - James A. Baker to Alice Baker Jones, 1932, 27508 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Annie Baker Eatman to cousin, Alice Baker Jones, 1951, 27507 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Col. J.G. James (Supt. of Texas Military Institute) to Judge James A. Baker, 1875, 27506 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Re: James A. Baker biographical sketch, 27505 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - On death of Capt. James A. Baker, 1941, 27504 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series II: Newsclippings, scrapbooks and published materials,1920-1941, undated; 27494
  - Newsclips re: Capt. James A. Baker death, 1941, and resolution by Guardian Trust Co., 27502 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Newsclips re: William M. Rice, 27501 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - The Patrick Case by Capt. James A. Baker, 27500 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Prince Edward County, Virginia by Archibald McRobert, 27499 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Philosophical Society of Texas Proceedings, 1941, 27498 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Scrapbook 1: Lincoln's death; Hurricane; 1920s-1930s, 27497 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook 2: Albert Patrick trial for the murder of William Marsh Rice, 27496 (Box 3)
  - Oversize newsclippings and ephemera [loose], 27495 (Box 4)
- Series III: Family photographs, 1870-1940, 27480
  - Capt. James A. Baker in uniform (Texas Military Institute) c. 1870s, 27493 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Judge James A. Baker, Mrs. Alice Graham Baker, and children James A. Baker Jr. and Mary (Minnie) Baker, ca. 1920?, 27492 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Two Houston newspaper clippings of photos of Miss Alice Baker and Mrs. Alice Graham Baker, ca. 1920, 27491 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Oversize photographs, 27481 (Box 2)
    - Newsclipping: King Nottoc Ball IX, Nov. 7, 1907, Houston Daily Post, featuring King Hon. Hiram Garwood and Queen Alice Graham Baker (color copy only), 27490 (Box 2)
    - No-tsu-oh, Nov. 7, 1907, featuring King Nottoc IX, Hon. Hiram Garwood and Queen Alice Graham Baker riding in horse-drawn buggy decorated with fresh flowers, 27489 (Box 2)
    - Palmer Chapel interior, June 1938, prepared for wedding of Alice Baker Jones to John Harris Meyers, Houston, TX (original and copy print), 27488 (Box 2)
    - Full length studio portrait of Alice Graham Baker (Mrs. James A. Baker), ca. 1900, by Davis & Sanford Studio, New York City (original and copy print), 27487 (Box 2)
    - Portrait of unidentified Baker or Graham female family member, taken The Falk Studio, The Waldorf Astoria, New York, n.d. (ca. 1910?), 27486 (Box 2)
    - Captain James A. Baker, Alice Jones Meyers holding Alice Graham Meyers, Alice Baker Jones, 1940, 27485 (Box 2)
    - Family photograph of Alice Baker Jones, Alice Graham Baker (Mrs. James A. Baker), and baby Alice Baker Jones [Meyers], c. 1915, 27484 (Box 2)
    - View of library in home of Capt. James A. Baker, 1416 Main St., n.d. (original and copy print), 27483 (Box 2)
    - Booklet of newsclippings on the death of Alice Graham Baker at age 67, May 9, 1932, 27482 (Box 2)